Washington State Department of Ecology:
My first work here includes working on developing and maintaining SPIIS, an application used across the spills program for environmental incident management like oil spills
SPIIS tech stack includes ASP.net, C#, SQL Database for coding. Azure Devops for code management and deployments. Trello board for managing service requests. GitHub copilot is also used to integrate AI development. 
We meet with every section of the program every month to discuss the current challenges that they are facing and brainstorm solutions with them.
My work for this application has been with stakeholders understanding requirements, translating them into tickets and working on them. I have also worked in optimizing the database layer for instance by implementing a one to many relationship, creating new tables, and stored procedures. Fixing and optimizing existing application features, adding new features to make sure that the response time during an incident is reduced.
While working on this application I collaborate with the whole team of devs, manager, and PM communicating my progress and blockers if any. 
My second work here includes working on a risk model whose end goal is to assess the effectiveness of tug escorts in cases of oil spills or other catastrophes in the sea caused by the vessels. I create ETL pipelines for this
This model includes categorizing vessels according to their behavior and activities, generating vessel traffic, simulating vessel movement after it loses power, identifying vessels carrying stuff like oil or cargo, identifying if vessels are being escorted or not according to the rules defined. 
The tech stack is Python, SQL Database for coding. Azure Devops for code management, ArcGIS for visualizing.
Created fast and efficient algorithms to clean vessel messages and create accurate vessel tracks. 
Figured out faster python libraries like polars to extract data containing millions of rows from database quickly. Optimizing writing final results to the database like using sqlalchemy, pushing in chunks, converting geometry columns from wkb instead of wkt
Optimized transform process for instance the weather data had millions of rows, so I figured out a way to load that in memory, and create a 3d matrix for instant access at every second of the momentum and drift simulation 
Created algorithms and brainstormed with stakeholders to identify when a vessel was laden and when a vessel was being escorted by a tug
The momentum and drift module simulates the vessel movement when the vessel loses propulsion. Researched the effects of wind and current on the movement of the vessel, implemented fast algorithms, OOPS concepts, python libraries like numba, polars to accurately and quickly depict the movement and condition of the vessel at every step. 
